Hey everybody, welcome to this listening
practice video in which I speak at
normal speed. So, I hope you're all
doing well today and that you're ready
to practice your English listening
comprehension. Today, I'm going to talk
about some resources that you can use to
learn English and not all these are
revolutionary things or anything like
that. You might already use these
things, but I just kind of want to talk
a little bit about what I do,
how I use these resources and how they
help me as a language learner. And so,
this can be helpful for you as well cuz
all you guys are learning English, of
course.
It's going to rain soon, so I got to be
quick. I hope it doesn't rain
while I'm filming this video. I think
the weather forecast said that it wasn't
going to rain for a couple hours or so,
but the sky looks pretty gray right now.
So, and before we start, remember to
check out my US Conversations podcast.
If you want my conversations that I have
with other people, usually other English
teachers, it's great practice for your
listening. So, if you feel like you can
already understand this content with the
subtitles and everything like that,
maybe it's time for you to practice with
conversations between two people. That's
the next step for you. So, if you want
that, you can click on the link down
below
and that'll take you to my US
Conversations podcast.
Okay, so let me talk about some
different content that you can use.
First of all, let me mention that you
should be thankful that for English,
there's a lot of content for
intermediate learners and I'm sure a lot
of you are at an intermediate level.
Even content like this is kind of like
intermediate content that intermediate
learners can use and that's great and I
say that because I'm learning Greek
right now and there is such little
content for people learning Greek. You'd
be amazed at how few resources there are
for people that aren't just absolute
beginners or whatever. So, just be
thankful because you have a lot of good
intermediate level content like my
podcast and a lot of other
content that's out there. So, be
thankful for that. So, let's talk about
translators. Translators are a great
tool when learning a language. I usually
use a combination of
Google Translate and WordReference.
These are the two that I like to use.
There are other good ones as well.
DeepL, I think is another one people
like. I think I used that briefly
when I was writing,
when I was translating the ebook, the
mini short stories that I wrote. I think
I used DeepL to help me with that.
But nowadays, I mostly just use Google
Translate and WordReference. So, the way
that I do this is that I translate full
sentences and phrases with Google
Translate, but for individual words, I
like to use WordReference because
WordReference gives you the different
definitions, sorry, the different
translations, the possible translations
of that word
for the different definitions of that
word. So, like the word right, for
example, could have different
definitions and it gives you like
translations of each of those different
definitions. So, it's really, really
good. But for full phrases and
sentences, I use Google Translate. So,
the way I kind of do this combination is
that I'll translate
phrases or sentences. Let's say I'm
writing in Greek and I need to translate
something. I'll use Google Translate,
but then if there's a word in that
translation that I'm not quite sure
about, I'll corroborate, I'll check that
with WordReference and I'll see, you
know, what is the what are the different
translations that WordReference gives me
for the word that I'm trying to that
Google Translate gave me and perfect, no
questions there. But sometimes, it gives
me some other words and I have to kind
of
discern and see which of those words am
I trying to say. And the way I'll do
this is I'll click on that
that translation, the different
translations that
WordReference gives me and I'll see cuz
then it'll go it'll do the opposite.
Like I'll click on the Greek word and
then it will give me the English
translations for that Greek word and
I'll see if this is really the word that
I was trying to use. And sometimes, I
click on the Greek word and then it
gives me like different words in English
from the word that I was trying to
translate and I go,
let me try one of those other words. And
so, and then I try the next Greek
translation and then I see, oh yeah,
that's the one that I really wanted to
say. So, that's kind of how I use that
combination. You can do that as well.
It's really helpful.
I think that these two tools are really
good. They're very helpful for
like when you want to write in a foreign
language, speak a foreign language. I
use them a lot when I'm writing.
They're just really helpful. And then of
course, like if I'm just listening to
something, reading something, I don't
understand a word, I can just type that
into WordReference, see what that word
is. Or if it's a full phrase or
sentence, I can put that into Google
Translate. So,
those are great
resources that you can use. I'm sure
some of you already use those resources.
The next one, this is one I talk about a
lot, LingQ, l i n g q, this website. I
use this for reading. It's a great
website to use for reading because
there's a lot of lessons already built
in there, but then you can import your
own
texts as well. And for this, I do want
to note that you want the paid version.
The free the free version, as far as I
can remember,
it's not that
robust. It doesn't have as much
of like what you need, whereas the
premium version is really, really good
and I use this. I pay for it. And it
gives you like a lot of different
lessons. I think you also have that on
the free version, but
you have a lot of different texts, but
really what's cool is you can import
your own texts and you can click on the
different words and the different words
in that text, once you click on them,
it'll show you the different
translations of that word in your
language. And so, instead of needing to
search every single word that you don't
know in another tab, you can just click
on the word and it gives you
translations and you can save those
those translations.
So, this takes out
a lot of the effort, it takes away a lot
of the effort that goes into reading in
a foreign language cuz one of the
hardest things is just reading and
wanting to
look up all the new words that you don't
know, but it takes so much time. You
have to keep closing the book, opening
up
you know, your your phone or whatever to
look for that word. It just makes
reading hard when it comes to reading in
a foreign language, but with this, you
can just click on the word right there
and it gives you the translation in your
language. So, I really like it. I use it
for reading. There's also audio for like
the the lessons that are already on the
site on the website. They also have the
audio of the person talking. So, that's
helpful as well. And when you click on
the word, like a word that you don't
know and you save the translation, it
turns the word yellow. So, the next time
you see that word in a different text,
it will also be yellow and it will
remind you, oh, you already clicked on
this word. You needed to see the
translation of this word. So, that's
kind of cool
cuz it you can kind of keep track of
words that you've already seen.
New words will be in blue. That means
that you haven't seen it on the website
yet. And then words that
you already know, like you've seen them
and you didn't need to look them up,
they're just like normal words. So, the
color system is pretty helpful as well.
So, I recommend that you try it. It's a
great way to read in another language,
in your case English. I do this and if
you haven't read in English or if you
find it hard to read in English, I think
you should really I really think you
should try this website.
The next one is Anki or Anki. I don't
know how people prefer to pronounce it.
I use this flashcard app for French in
particular.
You can use other flashcard apps as
well. And not everyone likes flashcards.
So, if you just hate flashcards, then
you can just ignore this.
But I think that there
is a usefulness to flashcards. There are
a lot of people that really benefit from
flashcards and I use Anki specifically
for when I'm trying to fill in gaps in
my speech. So, I will often talk to
myself in French and if there is
something that I don't know how to say,
I look it up and I see, okay, that's how
you say it and I'll save a flashcard
with that exact phrase or sentence that
I was trying to say. I don't usually
save individual words. I'll save a full
sentence or phrase that I myself was
trying to say. This is more powerful,
especially if it's your own sentence,
your own phrase because when I see that
flashcard, I remember, oh yeah, I
remember what I was talking about. I was
talking about this and I couldn't say
this. Those connections, those memories
make it more likely that you're going to
remember what that word is. It gives you
that context. And so, I find it really
helpful.
I review them once a day and it doesn't
take me that long as long as I'm not
adding a ton of new cards all the time.
But you can do it whenever, when you're
waiting in line for something, when
you're not engaged 100% in something and
you just have like a few minutes to
like, you know, you're just waiting for
something usually. That's when using
flashcards is really helpful. You can
fill in that those gaps where you're
just not doing anything in your day
and then you can, you know, learn a
language, learn English in your case.
So,
you don't need to necessarily use this
one, but I think that Anki is like maybe
the most
common one, if I'm not mistaken, the
most popular one that people use. And
there are other ones as well, but I find
it really helpful and the way this
system works is that it shows you the
cards when
around the time when you're going to
forget them probably. So, it has like
this system, this spaced repetition
system, we call it, and it tries to show
you the card at the optimal time. So,
it's not just reviewing the same words
every single day, right? It depends on
when the when you saw it last, and so,
it's pretty helpful. Uh lastly,
transcripts and subtitles. So, uh I know
that you're using subtitles right now,
cuz I have subtitles on this video, uh
but I want to talk about this. Uh
transcripts and subtitles are really,
really useful. Uh for example, like
learning Greek, uh I use uh transcripts
and subtitles uh of videos or podcast
episodes, and the way that I'll use them
is I'll use repetition uh with different
videos, podcast episodes, etc.
I'll watch the same thing or listen to
the same thing many times, sometimes
like seven, eight times even, and I'll
use the transcript to help me understand
every single word that is uh being said,
right? Or the subtitles. And um I'll
I'll try to understand every single
thing, and then I can just listen again,
or watch again, and try to understand
everything without the transcript,
without the subtitles eventually. That's
something you can do, for example, with
my podcast, uh even if you feel like you
can understand it uh pretty well, uh try
to understand every single word of the
episode. Use the transcript, uh you
know, see the the few words that you
missed, and then listen again, and then
uh pay attention, and then when those
words come up, you'll remember, "Oh, I
know that word. I know that word."
Right? That's really powerful for your
brain, that type of repetition and uh
just seeing those things that you
missed, learning them, listening again.
So, this is great. I use this uh as a
language learner, uh and that's why I
decided to put subtitles on this video,
uh or on these videos in general,
because they really are helpful. You
don't have to look at them. And a lot of
people not a lot of people, but some
people um they complain that "Ah, you
know, I don't want the subtitles. I just
want to practice without the subtitles."
That's great. If you want that, just
don't look. Just cover it with
something. It's not impossible to cover
the subtitles. I know people complain
about this, but I've done this, okay?
I'm a language learner as well. You can
watch content and just cover the
subtitles if you don't want them, okay?
So, um use subtitles, use transcripts,
and with this, you want to use
repetition. I can't stress this enough.
Repetition is extremely useful as a
language learner. Uh you know, listening
to the same thing uh over and over
again,
uh you know, you don't have to listen 10
times or whatever. Sometimes, I do like
to do that, but you don't have to do
that. But, listening a few times it it's
just really helpful, especially when you
have the transcript, when you have the
subtitles. Um
it really does help you learn words uh
with less effort, let's say. Um you can
uh internalize grammatical structures uh
that you have heard in that podcast
episode, that video, or whatever. Once
you hear it uh five, six, seven times,
uh like you're going to internalize a
lot of that, and even if you don't think
that you're learning a lot of grammar
explicitly, because you're hearing these
same phrases again and again, again and
again,
it it helps you
just understand the grammar in those
phrases intuitively, like without really
needing to explicitly learn that grammar
structure. And once you repeat something
multiple times,
uh the next time you listen or you
watch, you can already predict what the
person is going to say. You've already
heard it many times, and this is also
really helpful, cuz you can like say
things along with the speaker. You
already know what they're going to say,
and again, this just helps you
internalize things. It helps you learn
things. So, uh transcripts, subtitles,
repetition, uh all of that is just
really, really good, and like I said at
the beginning, be thankful that you have
a lot of intermediate level content
available uh for me, or sorry, there's a
fly right here. For me or other uh
English teachers uh that you can use
with transcripts, with subtitles, uh so
that you can uh do this type of
repetition uh with content that's
suitable for your level. Like this video
right now, I'm speaking just fast at
normal speed, but because there's the
subtitles, because the subtitles are
available, it's not the same thing as
just listening to a native speaker um in
real life without subtitles, right? This
kind of gives you uh that extra little
help, and and brings it down to more of
an intermediate level, where
me speaking, this is not like I'm
speaking at a lower level, but because
you have the resource of the subtitles,
it makes it accessible, and it makes it
good practice for someone at an
intermediate level. So, uh this type of
content is good for you if you're at an
intermediate level, and that's why I
usually, when people ask for B1 content,
I usually just point them to native
level resources that have subtitles or a
transcript, okay? Remember to check out
my US Conversations Podcast. It'll be
really helpful for you to start to get
accustomed to listening to more than one
person talking. So, that link is down
below, so click on that if you want to
check that out. Thank you all for
watching this video, and I'll talk to
you in the next one.